Finding Aid for Herbert H. Twining Papers, 1911 and 1927-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Herbert H. Twining Papers 1911, 1927-1980
Twining, Herbert H., 1900-1971.
2 oversize folders
3 linear feet
85431 Aa 2; UAl; Ac
Pioneer in the private camping movement, founder and director of Al-Gon-Quian Boys Camp on Burt Lake in Cheboygan County, Michigan, and officer in the American Camping Association. Correspondence, articles, speeches and photographs; also Camp Al-Gon-Quian materials, including program files, reports, roster files, and published yearly programs; materials of King family, missionaries in China; and plans of Twining home in Ann Arbor, Michigan, originally designed by Albert Kahn and his associate Malcolm for Louis A. Strauss.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Rozella Twining (donor no. 6438 ) in 1980 and 1984. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is open to research.
A pioneer in the private camping movement, Herbert H. Twining was the founder and director of the Al-Gon-Quian Boys Camp, 1925-1967. An Ann Arbor resident and University of Michigan graduate (1923), he was elected the first national president of the American Camping Association (ACA) in 1935. He later served as finance committee chairman and executor director of the ACA and was an advisor on the National Parks Board for several years.
The camp founded by Twining is located on Burt Lake in Cheboygan County. It was originally started as a private boys camp, and gained a prominent reputation over the years, as the sons of such important families as the Proctors and Gambles of Cincinnati, the Wrigleys of Chicago, and the Strohs of Detroit and Grosse Pointe were campers there, as well as the children of Alvin Bentley, C.S. Mott and G. Mennen Williams. Such notable University of Michigan figures as Ben Oosterbaan, Dr. Roger Howell, Roscoe Bonisteel and Deans Stason and James B. Edmonson have served on Twining's staff. Following his retirement in 1967, the camp was taken over by the Ann Arbor Young Men's and Young Women's Christian Associations.
The papers of Herbert Twining, except for an earlier family letter from 1888, date from the 1920s to 1980. The collection is broken down into a series of personal and family materials, a series on Camp Al-Gon-Quian, 1931-1967, and photographs.
Subjects:
Al-Gon-Quian Boys Camp (Burt Lake, Mich.); American Camping Association.; Architecture, Domestic.; Camps.; Cheboygan County (Mich.); China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Missionaries--China.; Strauss, Louis Abraham, 1872-1938.; Twining, Herbert H., 1900-1971.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Al-Gon-Quian Boys Camp (Burt Lake, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Au Gres (Mich.)--Buildings.; Bartlesville (Okla.)--Buildings.; Industries--Michigan--Bay City.; Boat and ship industry.; Boats.; Burt Lake (Mich.); Business enterprises.; Camps.; Children.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Handicraft.; Interiors--Business enterprises.; Missions--China.; Oklahoma.; Picnics.; Restaurants.; Saginaw River (Mich.); Schools--Michigan.; Shack (Restaurant: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Shipping--Great Lakes.; Ships--Great Lakes.; Sports.; Telephone operators.; Twining (Mich.)--Buildings.; Young Men's Christian Associations.
Contributors:
Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal materials
  The Personal materials series contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, articles and speeches related to the Twining family. Among these materials is a book of family stories written by Rosella Klein (Mrs. Herbert) Twining entitled No Salt Added.
  - General file containing newspaper clippings and article related to Herbert H. Twining 1936-1971 (Box 1)
  - Articles, speeches and radio programs circa 1930s (Box 1)
  - Architectural plans for the Twining home in Ann Arbor 1911 (Folder Ac)
    (originally designed by Albert Kahn and his associate Malcolm for Louis A. Strauss)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous 1888, 1927-1968 (Box 1)
      (include family letter, 1888)
    - World War II correspondence re participation in US Naval Reserves 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    - Congratulatory letters on 40th anniversary of the founding of Camp Al-Gon-Quian 1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Twining, Rosella Klein (Mrs. Herbert)
    - Biographical notes on Herbert Twining 1980 (Box 1)
    - No Salt Added, book containing personal and family stories (1973) (Box 1)
    - King family miscellanea regarding China and other topics (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan programs and other published material from his days as a student (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Camp Al-Gon-Quian materials 1931-1967
  The Al-Gon-Quian series contains programs, bulletins and other printed material related to the camp as well as counselor reports, evaluations and other information concerning camp programs.
  - Miscellaneous printed material 1931-1963 (Box 1)
  - Easter Seal Camp and funds for crippled children
    - Correspondence and related materials 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Summer programs
    - Activities
      - Award presentations 1962 (Box 1)
      - Counselor's files
        - Instructions and information 1966 (Box 1)
        - Reports to camp director
          - General evaluations 1963 (Box 1)
          - Indian program 1963 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous ceremonies and campfire speeches (Box 1)
    - Information forms and contact letters used for each camper 1960-1967 (Box 1)
    - Roster file (include names and addresses of campers and counselors)
      - 1940-1967, 18 folders (Box 1)
      - Listing by city 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - Yearbook 1931-1932 (Folder Ac)
    - Newsletters (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Yearly programs, Camp Al-Gon-Quian 1925-1963 (Box 2)
  - Songbooks, Camp Al-Gon-Quian undated, 1930 (Box 2)
  - The Camping Magazine, 1935-1938, 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The photographs series includes photos of activities at Camp Al-Gon-Quian. Included are family photos, images of the Twining's Ann Arbor, Michigan, home, of "The Shack" (later the "Brown Jug") in Ann Arbor, of a telephone switchboard in Au Gres, Michigan, shipping in Saginaw River at Bay City, Michigan, views of Twining, Michigan and Bartlesville, Oklahoma, and scenes of missionary life in China, 1910s.
  - Personal
    - Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 3)
      (includes photos of Twining home and "The Shack" (later renamed the "Brown Jug"))
    - Au Gres, Michigan (Box 3)
      (includes photos of Hill family home, William Hill at telephone switchboard, and boy in Indian outfit)
    - Bartlesville, Oklahoma street scenes (Box 3)
    - Bay City, Michigan (Box 3)
      (includes photos of boats and ships in Saginaw River, shipyard, and launching, 1890s ?)
    - Bay City High School graduation 1917 (Folder UAl)
    - China photos 1910s, of King Family (Box 3)
    - China postcards 1910s (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Twining, Michigan (Box 3)
      (includes street scenes, store interior and exterior, picnic, and school)
    - Herbert H. Twining as a child and young man (Box 3)
    - Unidentified: soldiers 1890s and child (Box 3)
    - YMCA state conferences 1916-1918 (Folder UAl)
  - Camp Al-Gon-Quian
    (see also oversize folder UAl)
    - Archery and rifle shooting (Box 3)
    - Boating (Box 3)
    - Buildings (Box 3)
    - Campcraft (Box 3)
    - Groups (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous indoor activities (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous outdoor activities (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous sports (Box 3)
    - Riding (Box 3)
    - Woodworking and metalworking (Box 3)
    - Albums
      - 1927-1940 (Box 3)
      - 1935 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
    - Rolled photographs: White House Conference on Children and Youth 1930, 1940 Camp Al-Gon-Quian banquet, 1929 University of Michigan student group, circa 1923 (Box 3)